Finding Aid for John W. Henderson (1916- ) Papers, 1943-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John W. Henderson papers
1943-2001
Henderson, John W. (John Woodworth), 1916-
85201 Aa 2
John W. Henderson, professor of ophthalmology at the University of Michigan, arrived in Ann Arbor in 1942 as an intern and then resident before joining the faculty in 1948. He was chairman of the Department of Ophthalmology from 1968 to 1978. Henderson’s papers include files relating to his work with the Medical School and University Hospital, among them histories of ophthalmology at the university. Files detailing his work with professional organizations are well represented, notably the Michigan Ophthalmological Society, American Board of Ophthalmology, and American Ophthalmological Society. Also files relating to publications, lectures and presentations.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
7.75 linear feet
The material was received from Dr. Henderson in 1982 and 2003 (Donor No. 6606 ).
The material is open to research without restriction.
John Woodworth Henderson was born in Clarinda, Iowa, in 1916. He received his bachelor degree from Occidental College in 1937, and his M.S. and M.D. degrees from Northwestern University in 1942. In 1948, he was awarded a Ph.D. by the University of Michigan. Henderson came to the University of Michigan in 1942, serving first as an intern. Subsequently he became a resident in ophthalmology from 1943 to 1948, a faculty member in the Medical School starting in 1948, and chairman of the Department of Ophthalmology during 1968-1978. A distinguished member of his profession, Henderson served in a number of national organizations, often in positions of great responsibility.
The John W. Henderson papers date from 1943 to 2001. The papers measure 7.75 linear feet and have been divided into four broad series: Medical School/University Hospital Records, Professional Organizations, Publications, Lectures and Professional Presentations, and Personal.
Subjects:
American Academy of Ophthalmology and Otolaryngology.; American Ophthalmological Society.; Association of University Professors of Ophthalmology.; Carrow, Flemming, 1852-1929.; Eye.; Michigan Ophthalmological Society.; Michigan State Medical Society.; Ophthalmology.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Ophthalmology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.
- Medical School/University Hospital Records
  The Medical School/University Hospital Records (1969-1980; 2.0 linear feet), are arranged alphabetically by subject. They result mainly from Henderson's responsibilities as chairman of the Department of Ophthalmology. Of particular interest is a history of the department (see also the Publications, Lectures and Professional Presentations series) and early faculty member Flemming Carrow; medical staff meeting minutes (1971-1971; 1976-1980); material regarding the neural and behavioral sciences including review and search committee (1972-1975); and minutes of the University Hospital Director's Advisory Council (1975-1978).
  - Academic Affairs, Committee on
    - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Alpern, Mathew, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Carrow, Flemming (1852-1929)
    - Biography (chapter 2 in The University of Michigan Department of Ophthalmology: A Proud Heritage) (Box 1)
    - "The Forgotten Professor,", 1985 (Box 1)
  - Clinical Affairs Executive Committee, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Department of Ophthalmology histories, 1881-1981 (Box 1)
  - Department of Ophthalmology department planning, 1967-1980 (Box 1)
  - Doll, Louis: Correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 1)
  - Emergency Medical Services Review by joint Medical School-Hospital Task Force, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Qualification, Evaluation of, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Retreat
    - 1972 (Box 1)
    - 1973 (Box 1)
  - Falls, Harold F, 1992-1996 (Box 1)
  - Governance Mechanism Committee, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Handbook for Ophthalmology House Officers, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Hubbard, William N., M.D., 1970 (Box 1)
  - Integrated Premedical-Medical Program (Inteflex), 1975 (Box 1)
  - Laser Acuity Examination, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Medical Center Review Committee, Report to the President, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Medical-Dental Staff Meeting Minutes, 1972-1976 (Box 2)
  - Medical Service Plan
    - Background Volume, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Implementation, Department of Ophthalmology, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Medical Staff Meeting Minutes
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1976-1980 (Box 2)
  - Neural and Behavioral Sciences
    - Class, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Committee, 1971-1977 (Box 2)
    - Review and Search Committee, 1972-1975; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - System Review Committee, 1976-1979 (Box 2)
  - Neuro-Ophthalmology, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Ophthalmology Microsurgery, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Postgraduate Conference, television broadcast, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Report of the Coordinating Sub-Committee for Conceptual Review of Practices, Policies and Curriculum Teaching: A Careful Superficial Overview ("An All-Purpose Talk"), 1961 (Box 2)
  - Staff Survey (University Wide) Report of Results, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Ultrasonography Program, 1969 (Box 2)
  - United States Training Grant, 1964-1970 (Box 2)
  - University Hospital
    - Director's Advisory Council Minutes
      - 1975 (Box 2)
      - 1976 (Box 2)
      - 1977 (Box 2)
      - 1978 (Box 2)
    - Greater Detroit Area Hospital Council Study (Blue Cross/Blue Shield Study), 1976-1978 (Box 2)
    - Search for Director, Committee Report, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Veterans Hospital (Ann Arbor), 1957-1975 (Box 2)
  - Wayne County General Hospital, 1962-1973 (Box 2)
- Professional Organizations
  Professional Organizations (1969-1981; 3.4 linear feet) represented in the collection include the American Academy of Ophthalmology and Otolaryngology, American Board of Ophthalmology, American Ophthalmological Society, Association of University Professors of Ophthalmology, Inc., Michigan Ophthalmological Society, and Michigan State Medical Society. Material is arranged alphabetically by the organization's name and chronologically within each organization.
  - American Academy of Ophthalmology and Otolaryngology (AAOO)
    - 1955 (Box 3)
    - 1969 (Box 3)
    - 1970, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1971 (Box 3)
    - 1972, 2 folders (Box 3)
      (2 folders)
    - 1973 (Box 3)
    - 1974
      - Board of Councilors (Box 3)
      - Executive Research and Executive Committee (Box 3)
      - Interim Council (Box 3)
      - Neuro-Optic Course (Box 3)
    - 1975 (Box 3)
    - 1977
      - Long Range Planning Conference (Box 3)
      - Public and Professional Education Committee (Box 3)
    - 1978
      - Ophthalmology-Optometry Interface Committee (Box 3)
      - Publication and Professional Education Committee (Box 3)
    - 1979
      - Academy Meeting (Box 3)
      - Publication and Professional Education Committee (Box 3)
  - American Board of Ophthalmology (ABO)
    - 1968 (Box 3)
    - 1969 (Box 3)
    - Examinations and meetings, 1970 (Box 3)
    - 1972-1973, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1973 (Box 4)
    - 1974 (Box 4)
    - 1975 (Box 4)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - 1976 (Box 4)
    - 1978 (Box 4)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 4)
    - Articles of incorporation, by-laws, rules and regulations (Box 4)
    - Advisory Board for Medical Specialties, Inc., 1969-1970 (Box 4)
    - American Board of Medical Specialties, 1973-1976 (Box 4)
    - Oral Examination Committee, 1969-1975 (Box 4)
    - Committee on Associate Examiners, 1970-1974 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1983-1991 (Box 4)
    - General, 1959-1968; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - American Ophthalmological Society (AOS)
    - 1971 (Box 4)
    - 1972 (Box 4)
    - 1973 (Box 4)
    - 1974 (Box 4)
    - 1975 (Box 4)
    - 1976 (Box 4)
    - 1977 (Box 4)
    - 1978 (Box 4)
    - 1979 (Box 4)
    - 1980 (Box 4)
    - General, 1982-1989 (Box 4)
    - Howe Medal, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
  - Association of Academic Health Centers, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Association of University Professors of Ophthalmology, Inc. (AUPO)
    - 1969 (Box 4)
    - 1973
      - Ophthalmology-Optometry Committee (Box 4)
      - Ophthalmology Resident Education Committee (Box 4)
    - 1974, 3 folders (Box 5)
      (3 folders)
    - 1975 (Box 5)
    - 1976
      - General (Box 5)
      - Manpower Committee (Box 5)
      - President, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1977 (Box 5)
  - International Society of Neuro-Ophthalmology, 1976-1978 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Ophthalmological Society (MOS)
    - 1970 (Box 5)
    - 1971
      - Interprofessional Committee (Box 5)
      - Legal Committee (Box 5)
      - Minutes (Box 5)
    - 1972 (Box 5)
    - 1973
      - Interprofessional Committee (Box 5)
      - Legal Committee (Box 5)
    - 1974
      - General (Box 5)
      - Interprofessional Committee (Box 5)
      - Legal Committee (Box 5)
    - 1975
      - General (Box 5)
      - Legal Committee (Box 5)
    - 1976
      - General (Box 6)
      - Legal Committee (Box 6)
    - 1977
      - General (Box 6)
      - Legal Committee (Box 6)
    - 1978
      - General (Box 6)
      - Legal Committee (Box 6)
    - 1979 (Box 6)
    - 1980 (Box 6)
    - 1981 (Box 6)
  - Michigan State Medical Society (MSMS)
    - 1971 (Box 6)
    - 1972, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 1973 (Box 6)
    - 1974 (Box 6)
    - 1975 (Box 6)
    - 1976 (Box 6)
- Publications, Lectures and Professional Presentations
  Publications, Lectures and Professional Presentations (1945-1980; 1.6 linear feet) is an alphabetically arranged file representing many of Henderson's scholarly activities. As subjects were often returned to after a lapse of time, and because much was undated, many folders dates are approximate. Of particular note is the manuscript and related correspondence on Henderson's history of the Department of Ophthalmology.
  - Aneurysms, 1949-1970 (Box 6)
  - Aneurysm Course, circa 1964 (Box 6)
  - Brain Scanning, 1965-1966 (Box 6)
  - Carotid-Cavernous Fistula, 1958-1963 (Box 6)
  - Cerebro-Vascular Lesions, 1959 (Box 6)
  - Choice of Surgical Procedures, circa 1960-1978 (Box 6)
  - Clinical Problems in Neuro-Ophthalmology, circa 1967 (Box 6)
  - Exophthalmos, 1956 (Box 6)
  - Eye Banks (Lions Club), 1970-1979 (Box 6)
  - Eye in Neurologic Diagnosis, 1962-1970 (Box 6)
  - Eye Movement Disorders, undated (Box 6)
  - Fisher Syndrome, 1975 (Box 6)
  - Fundus Demonstration, undated (Box 6)
  - Horner's Syndrome, 1958-circa 1961 (Box 6)
  - Infections of the Nervous System and their Ocular Signs, undated (Box 6)
  - Intracranial Tumor, undated (Box 6)
  - Jensen Rectus Muscle Union, 1971 (Box 6)
  - Manuscripts, 1969-1970 (Box 7)
  - Medical University of South Carolina, Department Review, 1979 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Neural Control of Eye Movements, circa 1976 (Box 7)
  - Neuro-Ophthalmology: article and reviews, 1959 (Box 7)
  - Neuro-Ophthalmology Course
    - circa 1952-1978 (Box 7)
    - Harvard, circa 1970 (Box 7)
  - Neuro-Ophthalmological Problems, 1964-1965 (Box 7)
  - Northwestern University Lecture, 1976 (Box 7)
  - Ocular Hysteria and Malingering, undated (Box 7)
  - Ocular Motility, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Ophthalmology, undated (Box 7)
  - Ophthalmology Residency, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Optic Nerve Infarct, circa 1952 (Box 7)
  - Optical Neuritis, 1963-1970 (Box 7)
  - Optolcinetic Study, circa 1952 (Box 7)
  - Painful Eye, 1973-1977 (Box 7)
  - Papilledema, circa 1966-1974 (Box 7)
  - Pinealoma, circa 1967 (Box 7)
  - Practical Perimetry, 1953 (Box 7)
  - Selected Neuro-Ophthalmological Problem Cases (Box 7)
  - Snell Lecture, 1969 (Box 7)
  - Strabismus, 1961 (Box 7)
  - Thyroid Exuphthalmos, 1959 (Box 7)
  - The University of Michigan Department of Ophthalmology: A Proud Heritage
    - Manuscript, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, 1986-1995; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - "The University of Michigan Eye Center: A Centennial Project, 1881-1981" (Box 7)
  - Vertical Gaze Paralysis in Midbrain Lesions, undated (Box 7)
  - Visual Fields, 1980 (Box 7)
  - Visual Pathway, undated (Box 7)
  - Workbook, 1945 (Box 7)
- Personal
  Personal material (1943-2001; 0.75 linear feet) further documents Henderson's career through curriculum vitae, information about his appointments, and two scrapbooks of clippings, programs and correspondence pertaining to his tenure and retirement.
  - Clippings, 1946-1961 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence (includes photographs), 1976-1998 (Box 8)
  - Curriculum vitae, 2001 (Box 8)
  - Faculty/Staff appointments, 1958-1973 (Box 8)
  - Galens Honorary Medical Society, 1963 (Box 8)
  - Knowledge Assessment, 1968-1978 (Box 8)
  - Narcotics and Dangerous Drugs, Bureau of, US Department of Justice, Registration with, 1971 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Career (includes photographs), 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Retirement, 1 volumes (Box 8)
      (includes photographs)
  - Surgery Cases as a Resident, 1943-1946 (Box 8)